# **ANKIT V. MANERIKAR**

Hillsboro, Oregon, USA

**Contact**: +1 765 602 6962

**Email ID**: ankitmanerikar@gmail.com

**Website:** ankitvm.github.io

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

A PhD in Computer Vision with a wide research and industry experience in the field of Tomographic Image Processing, Robotics and Machine Learning spanning a period of fourteen years, with authorship in multiple publications and encompassing contribution to over ten labs and companies.

#### **EDUCATION**

Purdue University, USA	Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) Electrical and Computer Engineering	3.80/4.00	Aug 2023
Purdue University, USA	Master of Science Electrical and Computer Engineering	3.84/4.00	Aug 2017
Mumbai University, India	Bachelor of Engineering Electronics Engineering (First Class with Distinction)	81.52% (1 <sup>st</sup> Rank)	July 2015
SBM Polytechnic, India	Pre-University Course (Engineering Diploma) Industrial Electronics (First Class with Distinction)	89.26% (1 <sup>st</sup> Rank)	July 2012

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

**Advisor:** Dr Avinash Kak

Robot Vision Lab, Purdue University

Jan 2017 – May 2022

West Lafayette

**Title**: Graduate Research Assistant

## **Major Projects:**

# BAA-1703 Contract on Dual Energy ATR for Airport Security:

A DoHS (Department of Homeland Security) project to research deep learning and adaptive boosting methods for threat detection in airport checkpoint security using Dual Energy CT security screeners.

### Contributions:

- *GANecdotes Self-Supervised One Shot Learning for Automatic Segmentation of StyleGAN Images:* A novel SwAV-based self-supervised learning framework for one-shot segmentation of GAN images the proposed model outperforms baselines in terms of IoU (by 1.02 %) and speed (by a factor of 4.05).
- BagGAN A StyleGAN-based Data Synthesis Tool for Baggage X-ray Scans:

  This research focuses on a mitigating the data availability problem for threat detector design by using adversarial networks for annotated data synthesis of baggage CT scans for explosives detection.
- *DEBISim A Simulation Pipeline for Dual Energy CT-Based baggage Inspection Systems:* The initiative aims at designing a physics-based CT simulation framework for X-ray data generation to aid the testing/training of machine learning algorithms for threat detection with Single-/Dual-energy CT screening.
- Classifier Design for 3D Segmentation using Dual Energy X-ray Tomography:

  This project involves the design of improved classifier frameworks for X-ray based object detection using density and atomic number data from Dual Energy CT.
- ALERT TO-7 Adaptive ATR Initiative:

An ALERT-sponsored project on Adaptive Automatic Target Recognition (AATR) for CT-based Threat Object Detection Systems for airport baggage screening.

#### Contributions:

• Adaptive Automatic Target Recognition (AATR) for CT-Based Object Detection Systems:

This project was a part of the ALERT TO-7 AATR Initiative and involved the design of an Automatic Target Recognition System for adaptively identifying target objects of varying specifications. The design involves a hierarchical supervoxel segmenter coalesced with an AdaBoost classifier for threat object detection.

# • Hierarchical Visual SLAM for Hospital Robotics:

A robot navigation project in collaboration with Botzee Inc., a robotic think-tank aiming at building dense visual maps for modular robot navigation in hospital environments.

# **Major Publications:**

- Manerikar, Ankit, and Avinash C. Kak. "Self-Supervised One-Shot Learning for Automatic Segmentation of StyleGAN Images." *arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.05639* (2023). [pdf] [code] (*Under review by IEEE T-PAMI*).
- Manerikar, Ankit, Fangda Li, and Avinash C. Kak. "DEBISim: A simulation pipeline for dual energy CT-based baggage inspection systems." *Journal of X-Ray Science and Technology* 29.2 (2021): 259-285. [pdf][code]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Tanmay Prakash, and Avinash C. Kak. "Adaptive target recognition: A case study involving airport baggage screening." *Anomaly Detection and Imaging with X-Rays (ADIX) V.* Vol. 11404. International Society for Optics and Photonics, 2020. [pdf]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Fangda Li, and Avinash Kak. "A Spectrum-Adaptive Decomposition Method for Effective Atomic Number Estimation using Dual Energy CT." IS&T Electronic Imaging: *Computational Imaging VIII, IS&T International Symposium on Electronic Imaging,* 2020. [pdf]
- Li, Fangda, Ankit Manerikar, Tanmay Prakash, and Avinash Kak. "A Splitting-Based Iterative Algorithm for GPU-Accelerated Statistical Dual-Energy X-Ray CT Reconstruction." IS&T Electronic Imaging: Computational Imaging VIII, IS&T International Symposium on Electronic Imaging, 2020. [pdf]
- Li, Fangda, Ankit Manerikar, and Avinash C. Kak. "RMPD—A Recursive Mid-Point Displacement Algorithm for Path Planning." In 28th Intl. Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling. 2018. [pdf]

# • Digital Photogrammetry Research Group, Purdue University

Jun 2016 - May 2017

**Advisors:** *Dr Ayman Habib, Dr Melba Crawford* **Title:** *Graduate Researcher (Master's Degree)* 

West Lafayette

## **Major Projects:**

• SLAM-Assisted Coverage Path Planning for Lidar Mapping Systems:

The research for this project was centred on the development of an efficient Coverage Path Planner for Mapping Vehicles. The developed planner uses a variant of the Exact Cellular Decomposition Method using MSA optimality criterion to implement a routing algorithm to be used with online SLAM.

• Pseudo-GNSS/INS Systems for Terrestrial/Aerial Photogrammetry Using Online SLAM:

This implementation encompasses a SLAM-based Pseudo-GNSS/INS system for a Mapping Vehicle equipped with LiDARs and Cameras to operate in GPS-devoid environments. The system has been successfully implemented for indoor Lidar Mapping Systems on a Roomba ICreate2 and using Velodyne 3D LiDARs.

# **Major Publications:**

- Shamseldin, Tamer, Ankit Manerikar, Magdy Elbahnasawy, and Ayman Habib. "SLAM-based Pseudo-GNSS/INS localization system for indoor LiDAR mobile mapping systems." In 2018 IEEE/ION Position, Location and Navigation Symposium (PLANS), pp. 197-208. IEEE, 2018. [pdf]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Tamer Shamseldin, and Ayman Habib. "SLAM-Assisted Coverage Path Planning for Indoor LiDAR Mapping Systems." *arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.04825* (2018). [pdf]

#### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

# **Purdue University – West Lafayette**

**Terms** 

**Title**: Graduate Teaching Assistant

Course: ECE 404 Introduction to Computer Security Jan 2021 – May 2021
 Course: ECE 382 Feedback System Analysis and Design Jan 2016 – May 2017

#### **PUBLICATIONS:**

• Manerikar, Ankit, and Avinash C. Kak. "Self-Supervised One-Shot Learning for Automatic Segmentation of StyleGAN Images." arXiv preprint arXiv:2303.05639 (2023). [pdf] [code] (Submitted to and under review by IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence).

- Manerikar, Ankit, Fangda Li, and Avinash C. Kak. "**DEBISim: A simulation pipeline for dual energy CT-based baggage inspection systems**." *Journal of X-Ray Science and Technology* 29.2 (2021): 259-285. [pdf] [code]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Tanmay Prakash, and Avinash C. Kak. "Adaptive target recognition: A case study involving airport baggage screening." *Anomaly Detection and Imaging with X-Rays (ADIX) V.* Vol. 11404. International Society for Optics and Photonics, 2020. [pdf]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Fangda Li, and Avinash Kak. "A Spectrum-Adaptive Decomposition Method for Effective Atomic Number Estimation using Dual Energy CT." IS&T Electronic Imaging: Computational Imaging VIII, IS&T International Symposium on Electronic Imaging, 2020. [pdf]
- Li, Fangda, Ankit Manerikar, Tanmay Prakash, and Avinash Kak. "A Splitting-Based Iterative Algorithm for GPU-Accelerated Statistical Dual-Energy X-Ray CT Reconstruction." IS&T Electronic Imaging: Computational Imaging VIII, IS&T International Symposium on Electronic Imaging, 2020. [pdf]
- Li, Fangda, Ankit V. Manerikar, and Avinash C. Kak. "**RMPD—A Recursive Mid-Point Displacement Algorithm for Path Planning.**" In *Twenty-Eighth International Conference on Automated Planning and Scheduling*. 2018. [pdf].
- Shamseldin, Tamer, Ankit Manerikar, Magdy Elbahnasawy, and Ayman Habib. "**SLAM-based Pseudo-GNSS/INS localization system for indoor LiDAR mobile mapping systems**." In 2018 IEEE/ION Position, Location and Navigation Symposium (PLANS), pp. 197-208. IEEE, 2018. [pdf]
- Manerikar, Ankit, Tamer Shamseldin, and Ayman Habib. "SLAM-Assisted Coverage Path Planning for Indoor LiDAR Mapping Systems." arXiv preprint arXiv:1811.04825 (2018). [pdf]
- Manerikar, Ankit, and Anandpara, Tanvi. "Design of a Practical Cat-righting Reflex (CRR) Model." *Procedia Computer Science* 45 (2015): 514-523. [pdf][GitHub]

#### **HONORS AND AWARDS**

Scholarship for Undergraduate Engineering (Years: 2012-13, 2013-14)

Best Student Paper Award "Particle Swarm Optimization in Control Systems Design",

IEEE Technomania 2013,

• Student Award for Academic Merit 1st Rank in B.E. (Electronics, DJSCoE), 6th Rank in University of Mumbai.

Juhu Lions Club Scholarship Award

1st Rank in Industrial Electronics
(Years: 2008-09, 2009-10, 2010-11, 2011-12)

#### **PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE**

Intel Corporation

**Title:** AI Algorithm Engineer - oneDNN

Aug 2023 – Present *Hillsboro. US* 

- Responsible for development and maintenance of oneDNN, a cross-platform performance library providing highly vectorized and TBB blocks for deep learning applications. [link]
- Developed new features and algorithms for the library which are optimized for Intel processors, GPUs and other hardware.

• Intel Corporation

**Title:** Deep Learning SWE Intern

May 2022 – December 2022 Santa Clara. US

- Conducted design and development to build and optimize AI software for the latest Intel x86 isa.
- Profiled distributed deep learning models to identify performance bottlenecks for state-of-the-art ML workloads worked specifically on the profiling of 3D-UNets and Vision Transformers.
- Worked on ML-based autotuning of DGEMM kernels for DL workloads for varying hardware specifications.

#### • Citizen Scales India (P) Ltd.

Title: Research Intern/Co-op

Dec 2011 - May 2012 SEEPZ, Mumbai

- Collaborated with a team of Firmware Engineers for design of a Moisture Analysis Device on an ARM7 platform.
- Implemented Regression-based algorithms for Temperature Compensation in Micro-Precision Weighing Scales.

#### • Technophilia Systems

June 2010 – Nov 2010

Mumbai

**Title**: Robotics Intern /Co-op

- Designed a Partial Gait Model for the Autonomous Navigation of a Biped.
- Designed navigation algorithms on an Atmega-XX platform and with a centroid-based object-tracking algorithm.
- Consultancy Projects:
- Rollform Equip. Pvt. Ltd. (Delhi, India): "Shear Measurement System for Rotary Blade Cutter" A. Choudhury.
- S M Technocrats Pvt. Ltd. (Delhi, India): "Efficiency Analysis for HF Induction Tube Welding" A. Choudhury.

#### **LIST OF OTHER SELECT PROJECTS:**

# • HMM based Smart Gesture Recognition using Wearable Inertial Sensors: (Gade Autonomous Systems, Mumbai)

- Developed a Machine-Learning algorithm using Hidden Markov Models to perform Gesture Recognition using wearable inertial sensors for adaptively learning a set of repetitive gestures made by an individual.

# • Indoor Place Categorization for Visual SLAM: [video] [GitHub]

(Course Project: BME595 (Deep Learning), Fall 2017 – Purdue University)

- Developed a Place Recognition Classifier using ResNet CNNs and inductive transfer learning to learn indoor visual landmarks during mobile robot navigation.

# • Optimal Constrained Coverage Path Planning for a Mobile Robot: [pdf] [GitHub]

(Course Project: AAE568 (Applied Optimal Control & Estimation), Spring 2016 – Purdue University)

- Developed a Pseudospectral Optimal Control based method for a Coverage Path Planning by a Mobile Robot.
- Simulated a MATLAB model to generate Optimal CPP Trajectory for obstacle avoidance and complex boundaries.

#### Position Control Using Ultrasonic Levitation Assembly: [video]

(Undergraduate Senior Project, University of Mumbai.)

- Designed a Contactless Precision Position Control system harnessing sound waves to suspend particles in mid-air.
- Developed digital controller code for the levitation system using a Tiva C-series ARM processor.

# • A Portable Soil Health Monitoring System for Dynamic Soil Mapping: [video]

(Presented at Texas Instruments IIADC, 2014)

- Implemented a portable UV-VIS spectrophotometer system allowing on-field spectral analysis of soil.
- Developed a sensing mechanism for measurement of soil OC (Organic Carbon) content using NIR Spectral Peaks.
- Designed an optoelectronic system as well as signal conditioning circuits for system operation.

#### **SKILLS:**

• Core Programming

• Computer Vision

• Machine Learning

• Computer Graphics/Simulation

Robotics

Developer Tools/IDEs

• Cloud Computing

**Python** (Expert), C++ (Expert), C (Proficient), Matlab (Proficient).

OpenCV, PCL, PyTorch3D.

PyTorch (Expert), TensorFlow, scikit-learn, OpenVINO, oneDNN.

Qt, MayaVi, ASTRA, Simulink.

ROS (Expert), Gazebo, ARIA

VSCode, PyCharm, Eclipse IDE, AVR-gcc.

Openstack (Expert), Eucalyptus, AWS.

#### **REFERENCES:**

(Available upon request.)